James S. Klar Photograph Collection
© 2005 University of Connecticut
James S. Klar Photograph Collection.
undated, 1974-1976.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Klar, James S.
5 linear feet.
Born in Greenfiled, Massachusetts on 30 May 1912, James Shepard Klar received his landscape architecture degree from the University of Massachusetts in 1934, and worked at different posts in state government throughout his career. When Klar retired in 1945, he was director of the state's Bureau of Program Development, where he was in charge of state assistance programs for local planning, urban renewal, and housing. In 1975, Klar received a grant from the Connecticut Commission on the Arts to photograph 75 railroad stations in southern New England and prepare a 100 picture collection for exhibition. The photographs taken in preparation for this exhibit, entitled “Down by the Depot” comprise the James S. Klar Collection.
MSS19900036
Biography
Born in Greenfiled, Massachusetts, on 30 May 1912, James Shepard Klar was the son of Walter Hughes and Mary Shepard Klar, who were well-known landscape painters in New England in the 1920s and 1930s. Klar received his landscape architecture degree from the University of Massachusetts in 1934, and worked at different posts in state government throughout his career. He married Majory Hemenway in 1932. The couple moved to Connecticut in 1945, eventually settling in the town of Bolton in 1976. When Klar retired in 1945, he was director of the state's Bureau of Program Development, where he was in charge of state assistance programs for local planning, urban renewal, and housing
As a youth, Klar engaged in photography as a hobby, and in later life used it to augment his professional career. After his retirement, he turned full time to photography, studying advanced photographic techniques at the University of Hartford from 1972-1973. He studied with Phil Zimmerman at the Natural Light Workshop in 1973 and with George Tice at the Apeiron School of Photography in 1974.
In 1975, he received a grant from the Connecticut Commission on the Arts to photograph 75 railroad stations in southern New England and prepare a 100 picture collection for exhibition. The photographs taken in preparation for this exhibit, entitled “Down by the Depot” comprise the James S. Klar Collection
Klar's photographs have been exhibited throughout Connecticut and Massachusetts. Klar also took first prize at the Heritage Village open contest in 1968, second prize in the South Britain (CT) annual open contest in 1969, and fourth prize in the Asahi Pentax International Contest (Japan) in 1970. His works, have been published in national magazines and are also represented in the permanent collections of the Springfield (MA) Museum of Fine Arts, the Mattatuck Museum (Waterbury, CT), the Lyman Allyn Museum (New London, CT), and the University of Massachusetts Fine Arts Center (Amherst, MA). In addition, Klar had a small gallery, The Silver Image Gallery, in his home, where his work could be seen by appointment
Klar died on 26 May 1985.
Scope and Content
In 1975, James S. Klar received a grant from the Connecticut Commission on the Arts to photograph seventy-five railroad stations in southern New England and prepare a one hundred picture exhibit. The photographs taken by Klar from 1975-1976 in Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and Vermont in preparation for this exhibition entitled “Down by the Depot” comprise the James S. Klar Photographs. The collection consists of six boxes of materials.
Arrangement
Series I: Mounted Prints ( undated, 1974-1976 ) contains ninety-two of the one hundred archivally mounted photographs which were originally exhibited under the title “Down by the Depot.” They are numbered R.R. 2A to R.R. 100. Box 1 also contains a mounted photograph of Versailles Station by photographer L. Jeff French.
Series II: Unmounted Prints ( undated, 1975 ) contains unmounted prints. Approximately two thirds of the unmounted prints are duplicates of the mounted exhibition prints. The remaining unmounted prints did not appear in the exhibition.
Series III: Print Marked for Cropping ( undated, 1975-1976 ) contains prints marked for cropping. The prints marked for cropping are divided into three folders. The first two contain copies of prints which appeared in the exhibit. The third contains prints marked for cropping which were not included in the exhibition.
Series IV: Negatives and Slides ( undated ) contains the negatives of the photographs contained in the collection and four unmarked slides.
Series V: Index Cards ( undated ) contains index card record of the exhibition photographs. The index cards, compiled by Klar, list each photograph by number (in the upper left hand corner) and by negative number of the photograph (in the upper right hand corner). The index cards also provide information on the photographic techniques and processes used by Klar in taking each photograph (front on index card), and the dates and places where each photograph was exhibited (back of index card).
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Cities and towns--Connecticut--Photographs.; Railroads--Photographs.; Railroad stations--Photographs.
Places:
Connecticut--Photographs.
Document Types:
Photographs.; Slides.
Occupations:
Photographers.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was bequeathed to the University by Mr. Klar's widow, Marjorie H. Klar, in 1988.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Mounted Prints, undated, 1974-1976
  - Ticket window, Versailles Station: by L. Jeff French, undated (Box 1)
  - Interior Hartford, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 1:, Othertype Photo No. 2A)
  - Box cars Lebanon, CT, 1975 May 8 (Box 1:, Othertype 3)
  - Grain elevators Lebanon, CT, 1975 May 8 (Box 1:, Othertype 4)
  - Wheels Lebanon, CT, 1975 May 8 (Box 1:, Othertype 5)
  - Facade over door New London, CT, 1975 March (Box 1:, Othertype 6)
  - Interior New London, CT, 1975 March (Box 1:, Othertype 7)
  - Telephone pole Windsor, CT, 1975 August 19 (Box 1:, Othertype 8)
  - Gondola car Windsor Locks, CT, 1975 August 19 (Box 1:, Othertype 9)
  - Berkeley Mills after fire Cumberland, RI, 1975 October 23 (Box 1:, Othertype 11)
  - Facade Woonsocket, RI, 1975 October 23 (Box 1:, Othertype 12)
  - Water tower Guilford, CT, 1975 November 1 (Box 1:, Othertype 13)
  - Three windows Old Saybrook, CT, 1975 (Box 1:, Othertype 14)
  - General view Plamer, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 1:, Othertype 15)
  - Facade Westerly, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 1:, Othertype 17)
  - Semaphore controls Groton, CT, 1975 April 30 (Box 1:, Othertype 18)
  - Full arch North Easton, MA, 1975 July 29 (Box 1:, Othertype 19)
  - Interior Wallingford, CT, 1975 April 23 (Box 1:, Othertype 20)
  - Roof detail Wallingford,CT, 1975 April 23 (Box 1:, Othertype 21)
  - General view Canaan, CT, 1975 June 21 (Box 1:, Othertype 22)
  - Crossing Canaan, CT, 1975 July 2 (Box 1:, Othertype 23)
  - Entrance Allston, MA, 1975 November 4 (Box 2:, Othertype 24)
  - Vines on wall Allston, CT, 1975 November 4 (Box 2:, Othertype 25)
  - Sign Bennington, VT, 1975 July 20 (Box 2:, Othertype 26)
  - Arches Bennington, VT, 1975 July 20 (Box 2:, Othertype 27)
  - Freight station Bristol, VT, 1975 Summer (Box 2:, Othertype 28)
  - Water tower Canaan, CT, 1975 July 2 (Box 2:, Othertype 29)
  - Timetable Canaan, CT, 1975 July 21 (Box 2:, Othertype 30)
  - Facade Colchester, CT, 1975 May 7 (Box 2:, Othertype 31)
  - Freight office Danbury, CT, 1975 November 6 (Box 2:, Othertype 32)
  - General view East Granby, CT, 1975 August 19 (Box 2:, Othertype 33)
  - White railings on railroad car Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 34)
  - Lion Gardiner car Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 35)
  - Baggage car with sign Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 36)
  - Snowplow Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 37)
  - Old car behind trees Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 38)
  - “Watch Your Step” Essex, CT, 1976 February 26 (Box 2:, Othertype 39)
  - Locomotive wheels Essex, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 2:, Othertype 40)
  - General view Forestville, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 2:, Othertype 41)
  - General view Gilbertville, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 2:, Othertype 42)
  - Wallpaper Gaylordsville (New Milford), CT, 1975 November 6 (Box 2:, Othertype 43)
  - Switch Tower, general view Groton, CT, 1975 April 30 (Box 2:, Othertype 44)
  - Dispatcher Groton, CT, 1975 April 28 (Box 2:, Othertype 45)
  - Paint texture Groton, CT, 1975 April 30 (Box 2:, Othertype 46)
  - General view Johnson, VT, 1974 October 1 (Box 2:, Othertype 47)
  - Flags Hartford, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 2:, Othertype 48)
  - General view North Kingston, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 2:, Othertype 49)
  - Windows in ceiling North Kingston, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 3:, Othertype 50)
  - Ticket window North Kingston, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 3:, Othertype 51)
  - Padlock New London, CT, 1975 April 23 (Box 3:, Othertype 54)
  - Bench New London, CT, 1975 March (Box 3:, Othertype 55)
  - Amtrack, car New London, CT, 1975 March (Box 3:, Othertype 56)
  - Detail of arch and seat North Easton, MA, 1975 July 29 (Box 3:, Othertype 57)
  - Signal tower, general view Old Saybrook, CT, 1975 June 10 (Box 3:, Othertype 58)
  - Signal tower detail Old Saybrook, CT, 1975 June 10 (Box 3:, Othertype 59)
  - Two girls and crossover Plainville, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 3:, Othertype 61)
  - Facade Peacedale, RI, 1975 July 24 (Box 3:, Othertype 62)
  - General view Sheldon, CT, 1974 (Box 3:, Othertype 63)
  - One Way Fare Simsbury, CT, 1975 August 19 (Box 3:, Othertype 64)
  - Curved corner Stafford Springs, CT, 1975 November 5 (Box 3:, Othertype 65)
  - General view Wallingford, CT, 1975 April 23 (Box 3:, Othertype 66)
  - General view Warren, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 3:, Othertype 67)
  - General view Waterbury, CT, 1975 November 8 (Box 3:, Othertype 68)
  - Brick detail Waterbury, CT, 1975 November 8 (Box 3:, Othertype 69)
  - Arches and columns Westerly, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 3:, Othertype 70)
  - Bench detail Westerly, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 3:, Othertype 71)
  - Pagoda roof West Barnstable, MA, 1975 September 15 (Box 3:, Othertype 72)
  - Stovepipe West Barnstable, MA, 1975 September 15 (Box 3:, Othertype 73)
  - General view West Brookfield, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 3:, Othertype 74)
  - Truck chains West Brookfield, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 4:, Othertype 75)
  - General view under trees Westboro, MA, 1975 July 31 (Box 4:, Othertype 76)
  - Freight station with telephone pole: Windsor, CT, 1976 August 19 (Box 4:, Othertype 77)
  - Office interior Woonsocket, RI, undated (Box 4:, Othertype 78)
  - Log end texture study Colchester, CT, 1975 May 7 (Box 4:, Othertype 79)
  - Balustrade Colchester, CT, 1975 May 7 (Box 4:, Othertype 80)
  - Peekhole Newton Highlands, MA, 1975 July 31 (Box 4:, Othertype 82)
  - Signal tower Buzzards Bay, MA, 1975 September 15 (Box 4:, Othertype 83)
  - Steps Deep River, CT, 1974 September 27 (Box 4:, Othertype 84)
  - General view, Gaylordsville New Milford, CT, 1975 November 6; mounted on one board (Box 4:, Othertype 85)
  - Sunlight on first floor New Milford, CT, 1975 November 6; mounted on one board (Box 4:, Othertype 86)
  - Stairwell, Gaylordsville New Milford, CT, 1975 November 6 (Box 4:, Othertype 87)
  - Beech tree and cart North Kingston, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 4:, Othertype 88)
  - General view Millis, MA, 1975 July 29; mounted on one board (Box 4:, Othertype 89)
  - Stone detail Millis, MA, 1975 November 8; mounted on one board (Box 4:, Othertype 90)
  - Clock detail Naugatuck, CT, 1975 November 8 (Box 4:, Othertype 91)
  - Delapidated walls New London, CT, 1975 March (Box 4:, Othertype 92)
  - General view North Easton, MA, 1975 July 30 (Box 4:, Othertype 93)
  - Entrance, Central Falls\Pawtucket, RI, 1975 October 23 (Box 4:, Othertype 94)
  - Interior Shannock, RI, 1975 July 24 (Box 4:, Othertype 96)
  - Roofs and tower Stoughton, MA, 1975 July 30 (Box 4:, Othertype 97)
  - Iron post detail Windsor, CT, 1975 August 19 (Box 4:, Othertype 98)
  - Interior ceiling detail Woonsocket, RI, 1975 October 23 (Box 4:, Othertype 99)
  - Tower North Bennington, VT, 1975 Summer (Box 4:, Othertype 100)
- Series II: Unmounted Prints, undated, 1975
  - Old 97 Essex, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 5:, Othertype 9)
  - Platform with Capital Hartford, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 5:, Othertype 10)
  - General view Palmer, MA, 1975 November 5 (Box 5:, Othertype 15)
  - Tower and car Chatham, MA, 1975 September 16 (Box 5:, Othertype 16)
  - Lavatories North Kingston, RI, 1975 April 22 (Box 5:, Othertype 52)
  - Radiator New Berlin, CT, 1975 April 23 (Box 5:, Othertype 53)
  - Victorian house Palmer, MA, 1975 November 4 (Box 5:, Othertype 60)
  - Brackets Lakeville, CT, 1975 June 21 (Box 5:, Othertype 81)
  - Platform with sign and view of capital Hartford, CT, 1975 Summer (Box 5:, Othertype unnumbered)
  - Union Station, general view Canaan, CT, undated (Box 5:, Othertype unnumbered)
  - Caboose, “Olde Dolls and Toys” no location, undated (Box 5:, Othertype unnumbered)
- Series III: Prints Marked for Cropping, 1975-1976
  - Numbered sequence, 1975-1976; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Unnumbered, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
- Series IV: Negatives and Slides, undated
  - Negatives (Box 6)
  - Unmarked slides (4)
- Series V: Index Cards, undated
  - Index cards for photographs